Let's go back to 15 + 10.
That is our standard time control.
And we're playing Wang, who I think is a
a stream regular. We've played him
before.
To those watching on YouTube, I'd like
to quickly apologize that the videos
recently have been coming out with a
slightly bigger gap.
Uh this is
for no dark reason. It's just because
I've been teaching in a lot of camps. I
went to Norway, so I'm super super busy
right now IRL. Um and I'll do my best to
come back to regular content making, you
know, every 2 days
very very soon. I have one more camp in
Atlanta that I'm teaching at this coming
week, and then the moment it's over,
things kind of settle down and I'll be
able to come back to
a more more regular routine. Appreciate
the patience.
And I do not appreciate the opening that
we are facing, the London system.
I don't recall if we faced the London
thus far in the speed run. Believe it or
not, I think we have not. Like I just
don't remember
um I just don't remember us facing it.
And
the thing about the London is that it's
it's less important what what you play
with black against it, and more
important that whatever it is that you
choose to play, you know really well.
There are a million systems that you can
play with black.
Which system you choose largely depends
on your style. There are more aggressive
ways to play. There are more balanced
ways to play, but there is one system
that I recommend to everyone who who
wishes
to make London system players
uncomfortable.
And who wants to get a dynamic
unbalanced and relatively speaking
non-theoretical game. And all of this
starts with a move C5.
And this is the most combative response
against the London for obvious reasons.
We're immediately challenging white's
center. This isn't really a pawn
sacrifice. We'll do a little theoretical
examination after the game.
And I will say as a disclaimer, I'm not
too proficient uh in the theory of the
system in OTB games against good
players. I've mostly played the King's
Indian setup. But I really really like
C5 in rapid and blitz.
If white takes on C5, typically black
plays knight A6 and immediately is able
to reclaim the pawn with interest. White
plays one of several possible moves,
which is of course
uh E3.
And now you can play D5, which
transposes into what we can call the
main line, the most popular
continuation.
But the way to deviate
uh from
mainstream theory is to quickly position
our queen on B6. And we can do it
immediately.
But I like first taking on D4, creating
a pawn structure imbalance.
This creates an imbalance because it
leads to a situation where white has a
three on two on the queen side, and
black actually has, I don't say this
very often, a five on four
in the center and on the king side. Pawn
structure imbalances create dynamic
play. They create the possibility for
tactics, and this is already a step
forward when you're dealing with a
London system player. And now we
position our queen on B6. Now, if you've
seen London games, whatever you play
with black against it, you've probably
seen the queen come out to this square
in the London system. It's a very very
typical development of the queen because
on B6 it does a lot of things. It's out
of the way of the other pieces, but most
importantly, it's pressuring two pawns
at once. And this is as primitive as
this sounds, a drawback of the London
system. When the bishop comes out this
early, the B2 pawn is left without a
defender, and white actually has a
pretty difficult time finding a
defensive move which doesn't make
serious positional concessions. And the
move that a lot of less experienced
players play here automatically is B3.
We might face it in this game, but the
move B3 comes at a great positional
cost. First of all, it doesn't develop a
piece,
but most importantly, it tremendously
weakens the dark squares on the queen
side. C3, B4, A3. Pawns don't go
backwards, so the move B3, which I'll
talk about after the game,
is a common response, which I I think
already gives black a very comfortable
game. Knight to C3, along with the
sister move knight to A3, is the most
challenging, the most principled
response to queen to B6.
The idea is simple. If we grab this
pawn,
this leads to a very theoretical line.
We're not going to go into it. White
plays knight to B5 with very very
dangerous
uh consequences for black. There is a
ton of computer theory there. I don't
know what the current modern evaluation
is, but I'm pretty sure that you're not
supposed to take the pawn. I'm pretty
sure that even if we play all the engine
moves with black, white actually has a
very strong initiative there. We'll
explore some lines just out of
curiosity, but this is not the move that
I recommend.
There are a couple of possibilities
here.
Um one is to play D5 and contest the
center. I don't love D5 because white
can play the move knight to B5 and force
our knight to occupy a very awkward
square on A6. This also happens in the
Jobava London because then we'll not
never really be able to get rid of this
knight. We'll be completely frozen on
the queen side.
What are the other possibilities? We can
put the pawn on D6, and we can play this
sort of King's Indian style. We can play
D6 and then G6 and play all the King's
Indian moves.
And the good thing about that setup is
that we've forced the knight onto C3.
And typically with white in King's
Indian positions, you want to have D4 C4
included. And then the other option is
to play A6. I've recommended this to
some people. This covers the B5 square.
It's actually a very challenging move,
and typically A6 is paired with D5. So,
choose your pick. I want to go A6
because it is the least explored of all
the possibilities. Most of the time,
even pretty good players like 2000s are
are completely on their own at this
point. And that is exactly what we want.
I think this is a very underrated
system.
We will check with the newest Stockfish.
I haven't analyzed this properly in a
couple of years.
White has an edge if white plays this
absolutely perfectly, but very very few
people do. And even if he does, you get
a combative, interesting, dynamic game.
Ultimately, this is what you want.
Um if you're
not a grandmaster, if you're not a 2700,
your your primary objective out of the
opening isn't to get 0.00.
All right, that's the mistake a lot of
players make. It's to get a comfortable
position and a position that
you know, makes your opponent
uncomfortable. Okay, rook to B1. So, our
opponent defends the pawn without
weakening all of the dark squares.
Still, it's nice that we've garnered a
tempo and forced white to play this kind
of somewhat awkward move.
Okay, so once again,
we can play D6. There's nothing wrong
with that, but then why did we play A6,
right? Then A6 becomes a waste of time.
So, let's play this more consistently.
Let's go D5.
Let's see how our opponent chooses to
uh develop their pieces.
And there's a lot of positional
subtleties here
that newer players might kind of roll
their eyes at and uh might find a little
bit over their heads, but
once again, I want to remind you that
the whole concept of the speed run is
that most of my advice is based on
is is aimed at the level where I'm
currently located. Um and I'll still try
to explain things in very general terms
for newer players. Knight F3, as far as
I know, is an inaccuracy. Believe it or
not, this unbelievably natural
developmental move is a serious
positional inaccuracy. Who can explain
why? And first and foremost, what is the
move? What does it allow?
What does it allow?
And you might even object to the use of
the word allow. What does it mean it
allows something?
Because we're just developing our
pieces. What it allows is bishop to G4.
And why am I using the word allow
in this context? Bishop G4 is actually a
very unpleasant move. I'll show you an
analog in the Caro-Kann where something
very similar happens. The D4 pawn,
believe it or not, is a serious
weakness.
And it's a weakness
because the knight on C3 is preventing
the C pawn from inching upward and
protecting D4, as is very customary in
most London system lines. That's part of
the appeal of Queen B6. In London
system, typically white doesn't put the
knight on C3. White, of course, puts the
pawn on C3.
The defender of the D4 pawn primarily is
this F3 knight. If we can take it off
the board, then white will have
problems in the long run defending D4.
If white plays this very carefully, then
he can get out of it, but we're already
putting serious pressure on this pawn.
We can take the knight, but we don't
really have to. I think a better idea is
just to develop our knight and to
continue pressuring the D4 pawn.
Now, you might look at this and say,
"Well, doesn't white have the ability to
move this knight now? Isn't knight E5
something to be concerned about?" Knight
E5 might very well be the best move.
In fact, I think it might be the only
way for white to cleanly keep equality.
But after knight E5, we take the bishop
on E2.
And if white takes back with a queen,
then he drops the pawn on D4.
So, after knight E5,
bishop takes E2, white has to recapture
with the knight.
And at the very least in that position,
we can just play E6 and develop our
bishop, and we have a super comfortable
position, as some of you in the chat are
very accurately pointing out. This
resembles an exchange Caro-Kann.
And in fact, the London system has the
capacity to transpose
into the exchange Caro-Kann because you
get essentially the same pawn structure.
This is an exchange Caro pawn structure.
But bishop E3 is a sign that our
opponent isn't happy with his position.
He's going backward. He's overprotecting
the D4 pawn, and he's giving us just an
opportunity to develop our pieces to
ideal squares.
Again, you can take the knight on F3,
but I don't see the need to give away
the bishop pair. We're not really afraid
of white playing 95. That move doesn't
really carry any kind of venom. So,
let's continue developing our pieces. We
do this by playing E6.
G6 is not particularly good in this kind
of structure because we want to make
sure that our own center pawn is
reinforced. And of course, this bishop
if you're a Caro-Kann player, you should
know this belongs on D6 in these kinds
of structures.
Um
perhaps some of you, particularly newer
players, might might be attracted to the
look of bishop to B4 because it looks
like a more active move. But, bishop B4
actually justifies the placement of
white's rook. What you don't want to do
is give away your your dark-squared
bishop that easily because yeah, you
damaged white's pawn structure, at least
visually, but then the rook on B1
actually occupies an open file. Our
queen's going to be pushed away from B6,
and white will be able to use the
doubled pawns as a battering ram and
advance
the tip
the top pawn to C4 and contest the
center. I'll I'll show you
uh that kind of scenario after the game.
H3. Okay.
So, our opponent forces us to decide.
Again, we're adhering to the strategy of
not giving up the bishop pair without a
clear reason. I still don't see a reason
to give up the bishop pair. Where do we
go? Well, bishop F5 is possible, but I
kind of like the tension that we're
exerting on white's light-squared
bishop. So, let's drop it back to H5.
And this is a boring position from a
tactical standpoint, but as I've been
saying now for a couple of hundred
points, if you want to cross 2,000
and you want to climb at this level, you
need to know how to win boring
positions, right? You need to know how
to win grindy grindy maneuvering
positional games
because you cannot at this point steer
every game, particularly with black,
into the direction that makes you happy,
right? You just
you can't force it. Um and you have to
embrace embrace the suck if you're a
tactical player who finds these kind
this kind of chess to be dry and
insipid. And I'm that kind of player,
but I've kind of learned to enjoy
the the process of playing positions
that don't always make me feel
comfortable.
Okay.
So, our opponent is thinking
black is doing great here. Our pieces
are all nicely developed. Our next step
is to castle queen side and king side,
and then of course, we will
move on to the next step, which is to
develop a middle game plan.
And our middle game plan is is not going
to be to put more pressure on the D4
pawn because we can't do that. Our
opponent has protected it a thousand
ways, and I don't see any way for us to
exert more pressure on the board. We're
going to have to transition our play to
another side of the board. Okay, A3.
Not sure exactly what white wants. I
don't think B4
is is dangerous in the least because
well, first of all, it doesn't really do
anything. And second of all, the knight
on C3 is left without a defender.
But, if we wanted to defend against B4,
we could. And in fact, there is a move
that I really really like because this
is a move that I was going to propose
anyway. It's a move that I was going to
play after we had castled. But, in the
context of white playing A3,
I think this move makes even more sense
because it completely takes the sting
out of B4. Does anybody see what I'm
talking about?
And the fact that B4 leaves this knight
undefended is a big hint.
So, we need to make a move such that
after B4, we can exploit the undefended
knight. Well,
that basically means putting a a piece
on C8.
But, if we put the rook on C8, white
actually can still play B4.
Because there, you might spot the
discovered attack. Knight takes B4, but
then
white's rook pins the knight to the
queen, and white can simply move this
knight away, even to A2, and our knight
is going to be lost.
So, we kill two birds with one stone,
and we drop the queen back to C7.
This is a super important concept that
I'll write down and that I'll talk about
at length after the game, which doesn't
have a name, but it's the notion that a
piece can be good in a particular square
for a long time, and it can be very hard
to move that piece away because you
almost get emotionally attached to its
placement. You're like, the queen on B6,
it's pressuring D4.
But, that pressure has done its job.
It's allowed us to develop our pieces
nicely, and now it's time for the queen
to kind of seek greener pastures. It's
not doing quite as much on B6. It's sort
of overstated its welcome. On C7, it's
combining with the bishop. It's
pressuring the C file. It's stopping B4.
It's also protecting the E5 square,
which renders the move 95
rather unwise because it will drop a
pawn.
So,
I'm going to note this down.
Piece doing its job.
Okay.
Now, of course, we're going to castle.
There's a third thing that queen C7
does, which is that it paves the way for
the path of our own B pawn, right? We
can play B5. Why would we play B5 in
such a position?
Well, it's not really to play B4. Right?
Because if you advance this pawn to B4,
what do you achieve? White simply plays
A takes B4.
And all that you've done is created a
weakness on A6, an isolated pawn.
So, what is the purpose of playing a
move like B5?
Well, it's
nothing
overly profound. You just grab some
space on the queen side. You clamp down
on the C4 square, and you start slowly
squeezing white off the board, making it
more difficult for white to do what he
wants to do.
Queen D2 doesn't really achieve all that
much. Our opponent is connecting his
rooks.
We shouldn't overthink this. Let's
castle.
And this is the stage of the game where
our development is complete and where we
kind of start crossing
um our Ts and dotting our Is. That's I
think the best way to describe it. Where
it's not that we have already a big
plan, but we have some low-hanging
fruit. We have a couple of moves that we
can play almost without thinking that
clearly improve our position and set
ourselves up
for ultimately something more concrete.
What are those moves, right? Those are
the kinds of moves newer players
struggle to play because they don't
always see exactly what they achieve.
But, the point is you don't have to know
exactly what it achieves. You just have
to know that it won't damage your
position. And as some of you are
pointing out, rook AC8 is exactly one of
those moves. Put a rook on the C file,
you never know when this could come in
handy. And another one of those moves,
slightly more ambitious, is to play B5.
I like the move B5.
I like the move rook AC8. If you want to
be maximally flexible, then you should
play rook C8. If you want to be more
ambitious, then you should play B5. In a
real game, I would probably go B5. So,
I'm going to do it here as well. I'm
going to go B5.
Grab space.
Makes it harder for white to breathe.
Another one of those moves is H6, by the
way. Just make some luft.
Your instinct to this might be, well,
what about bishop takes H6? And that has
to be calculated on a case-by-case
basis. This is a sack that a lot of
players fear unconditionally, but it's
actually not always dangerous. And this
is a a case of bishop takes H6 not being
dangerous if you just calculate. So, for
instance, H6 takes takes takes,
and then we have this nice defensive
move bishop H5 to G6
in order to keep the knight on F6,
and white is at a complete dead end.
White has no pieces in the attack, and
there are no mating squares.
So, in that position, the move knight G5
just doesn't pose any threats because H7
is under lock and key.
Okay.
And let's see what our opponent chooses
here.
Super comfortable position.
Why is it difficult for white to find a
move? Because it's not clear what to do.
We have no targets in the position. If
white tries to move this knight away,
typical plan to move the knight away and
go C3, then white gives up this very
important E4 square, and we can put a
knight there with tempo.
And then we can follow up with F5, and
then we can start playing on the king
side, actually.
Is bishop G5 annoying for black? Yeah, I
I was waiting for someone to bring that
up. Bishop to G5 is actually a decent
move. I would consider it myself
in in a real game. There's a
somewhat tactical reason that bishop G5
might fail,
which is the response knight to E4.
We'll we'll calculate that if he plays
it.
But, the funny thing is, bishop G5
doesn't even really threaten bishop
takes F6.
Because after GF, we get the bishop
pair,
and visually, our king side pawn
structure is ugly, but it's essentially
unexploitable, which is another concept
that you really have to wrap your head
around, which is that
when you weaken your king side like
that,
you shouldn't rule out the move just
because it looks ugly and the queen is
coming to H6. And I'll show you some
lines after the game. White's pieces are
so passive that even in the event of
bishop G5 bishop takes F6, white
wouldn't have the machinery to really do
anything to bother us on the king side.
B4, that is quite a move. That is quite
a move. It's a very weakening move, and
I think we can exploit it automatically
by playing rook C8.
Now, which rook, you might ask? Well,
there's a case to be made for both
rooks, actually.
Let me think about this for a second. My
instinct is rook AC8 to keep the other
one on the king side. You never know
when it could come in handy on the king
side. On the other hand, rook FC8 keeps
this rook on the A file,
and there is a non-zero possibility that
the A file opens up. We could open it up
later with A5, not now because B5 would
fall, or white could play A4 and A takes
B5, and then we would be thankful that
we kept this rook on a closed file.
These are hard decisions. It's not like
GMs have a secret key that allows me to
make an informed decision about where to
put my rook.
The more I look at this, though, the
more I can appreciate rook FC8 because
the action is going on on the queen
side. The king side is not where the fun
is at, not where the party is at.
So,
huh.
Very hard decision, actually. I I don't
know. I'll be honest. I don't know which
move is better. They're probably about
equivalent, and you don't want to waste
too much time on it. We're already quite
short of time.
Hm.
Let's go rook f3. Let's sort of follow
the positional rules,
which dictate that okay, action is
happening on the queen side, so let's
assemble our pieces where the fun is
happening.
And black is already much better. Of
course, the other drawback of the move
b4 is that it creates a massive weakness
on c4, where eventually we would want to
put a knight. Easier said than done.
What is the fastest way of getting a
knight to c4? It's a worthy question to
ask. There is a way to do it in three
moves. We could play knight f6 to d7 to
b6,
and then we would be ready to put it on
c4. But of course, you don't want to put
it on c4 as long as there's a bishop on
e2.
Nimzowitsch talked about this and
I'll talk about this a little bit after
the game as well. You want to occupy a
weak square with pieces.
When you occupy a weak square with a
pawn, Nimzowitsch compared it to going
to the dentist and like getting a cavity
filled. So, if you imagine the knight
getting to c4 and then white taking it
and you taking it with a pawn, you're
not extracting
no pun intended, get away from the
dental theme, you're not extracting the
benefit of occupying a weak square
because when a pawn sits on it, there's
no square. You can't use that square for
your benefit. Hopefully you're you're
appreciating the general concepts and
I'll make it more concrete after the
game. And maybe we'll even get a chance
to
carry this out during the game.
If that pawn is a passed pawn, it's
different. Of course, and and and there
are exceptions to every rule that I
share. There are situations where yeah,
you you can take back with a pawn. Maybe
I'll even find one after the game.
Yeah, it's going to be a fun analysis
because I'll be able to talk about a lot
of important foundational positional
concepts.
Now,
of course,
you might also notice that after knight
d7 knight b6, we have
a tool available at our disposal to
deflect this bishop. We can trade our
bishop for the knight. And either white
has to completely ruin his structure.
And given the weaknesses already in
existence on the queen side, this makes
white's position even harder to win. Or
after bishop f3,
it allows us to put the knight on c4.
So, let's think. Many, many good moves
here. Give me 30 seconds here just to
try to try to squeeze the most out of
this position.
It's too early to think about tactics,
but there's just so many good candidate
moves here. And I don't want to make
I don't want to do something that gives
white unnecessary counterplay.
And it's very easy to do that, by the
way,
when you have a lot of good options. I
don't love knight d7, actually. The
reason I don't love it is because I like
the placement of this knight. I I like
the way this knight is placed because
it's it's ready to jump into e4 the
moment this knight moves. So, that's
that's not to my liking.
We could play bishop takes f3 already
and just get rid of this knight. Also,
don't love giving away the bishop pair.
Mhm.
Bishop f3 is not bad at all, I think,
the more I look at it.
You know what move I really, really like
here?
Knight to b8.
I really like the look of this move.
Maybe a mistake. I I I you know, th-
these positions are are very hard to
play accurately, but hopefully it's it's
halfway decent.
What are we doing? Well,
we are getting the knight around to b6.
You might say, "Well, didn't I just say
that this could be done in three moves?
Why am I doing it in four?" Well,
there's two things to keep in mind. The
center is closed, which means that the
value of each individual tempo is
greatly diminished. We can afford to do
something in four moves when we could
have done it in three. And as I just
mentioned, I like the placement of the
other knight. And the final thing is
that it also opens up the c-file, which
increases the pressure on the knight,
which makes it even harder for white to
move out. Bishop d3 is an impatient move
by our opponent. Bishop takes f3 is
begging to be played. We should keep in
mind that this gives white a sliver of
counterplay on the king side.
White will probably play rook to g1. I
think this is what our opponent is
banking on, but
even if white plays that, we can always
put our g-pawn on g6. And because
white's pawn structure is so bad, white
is unable to use his pawns to shatter
our king's our our pawn skeleton on the
king side. And I just don't feel like
white has enough pieces to smash through
with a set with sacrifices. And I'm
doing this without calculation.
I think we can afford to continue our
plan with knight b7.
But we need to
find the right time to play g6.
A move that I think if you're newer to
chess,
and you're watching this, you're like,
"G6, man, I I but I was taught never to
make a move like this unless you
absolutely have to." And what you're
watching is an exception to the rule.
In fact, the pawn on g6 is much safer
than it is on g7 because on g7 it can be
targeted with moves like bishop to h6.
Um
I'll delve into this more after the
game. Okay, rook to g1. So, right now
there are still no threats. And you
could say, "Well, why don't we wait for
white to play bishop h6 and only then
play g6 to conserve time?" And that's a
reasonable point, but I don't see the
need to procrastinate with this. I think
if we already played g6, we don't have
to worry about you know, maybe even a
sack on g7 or something. You never know
what kind of stuff can hurt can hurt you
in time pressure.
So,
you know, my my cautious side of the
brain says to play g6. King h8, also a
very good defensive move. Lots of
options here that allow us to make sure
our king is completely safe.
Mhm.
King h8, let's go g6. Let's let's uh
check this one off our list.
I'm anticipating h4. I think most people
would go h4 here,
but h4 is an empty move. It doesn't
create a threat.
And it doesn't create a threat because
h5 is controlled by knight d2. Okay,
also reasonable.
Now, I think we need to be very
concrete. We can play knight b6 knight
c4 as we intended earlier, but I think
there's a nice defensive move here that
we could throw in to make it difficult
for white to develop his king side
counterplay.
And that move
is knight to h5.
Knight to h5.
Knights on the rim are amazing, as the
expression goes.
And h5, what is would
what is what are we doing?
And didn't I say that I like the
placement of the knight on f6? Well,
things changed when we took on f3.
Because when we took on f3, one of the
small drawbacks of that move was that
this f-pawn is now restricting our
knight. So, our knight, again, same
concept, when we played queen to c7, it
was good at one time, but the structure
changed and now it's time for the knight
uh to fulfill another role. And the role
that it's fulfilling right now is it's
preventing white's knight from jumping
into the attack. Notice how the knight
on h5, even though it's on the rim, I
have a great example of that,
is
restricting its counterpart, which is in
the center.
Um which happens sometimes.
And it happens because our other pieces
are superior. Because we're controlling
the g3 square with three pieces, white
only with two, the pawn on the rook at
g3 is impossible, same reason knight f4
is impossible. White is essentially
frozen in a place on the king side. But
there is a deeper reason why I like that
h5. And this is really advanced. Not
saying this to toot my own horn, just to
give you some context, but
our opponent took this in another
direction, f4. Clearly he's intending
the move f5. We need to be tactically
alert. F5 is not a move that we want to
allow because you can't take back with a
g-pawn. EF, there's bishop takes f5.
Last thing we want is to give black
white counterplay. Let me think for a
second.
I have a really cool move.
Oh, man, I think I see a really, really
nice idea.
But let me just confirm that it works
because at this point we're starting to
rely a little bit on our calculation and
tactics. Here's the move.
We are going to play
mhm.
Th- So, the simple way is to play king
h8, but I don't want to be simple. I
want to be sophisticated. And
sophisticated sometimes means mistake,
but hopefully not this time. Queen d8.
And this actually was the third thing
that I wanted to point out before our
opponent played f4, which is that when
we play knight h5, it actually opened up
a pathway for our queen to join the king
side attack. Remember, white's the one
with the ruined king side pawn
structure, which means theoretically, we
are the ones who should be attacking on
the king side, and that's what I'm
starting to do. And I was going to say
that it indirectly prevents the move
knight to g3. There is, I think, a
beautiful idea here.
There is a business-like move. You can
do this in a very straightforward
fashion, or you can do this in beautiful
fashion. Does anybody see the tactical
solution here?
So, the the straightforward move is
queen to h4 because it threatens
checkmate. But I think there is a much
more beautiful move, which is knight
takes f4 bishop takes f, and then queen
h4
with a double attack.
It threatens checkmate. It threatens the
bishop on f4.
bishop on f4. Let me just double-check
this.
All right.
Let me double-check this.
Takes, takes, queen h4.
Mhm.
I don't see a defense. I don't see a
defense. I think it works.
Because if it doesn't work, we lose the
game. That's the thing. That's the
danger of these types of tactics.
And
it's inevitable that you have to rely on
this kind of stuff. You you cannot avoid
it. Even if you play the greatest
positional game, and you maneuver like
Karpov and Capablanca, and your opponent
is biting the dust, at some point you're
going to have a moment where you have to
convert your advantage.
And that means calculation, tactics,
etc.
I By the way, I think queen h4 is a much
is a better move. There is a crazy
resource that white has. I saw it, but I
I can't resist. It's too beautiful of a
move. It's too beautiful of a move.
But it does allow one little defensive
resource, which I think gives white a
glimmer of hope,
which the move queen h4
does not allow.
And you guys can figure this out on your
own. We'll see if our opponent finds it.
I'm regretting it slightly because this
violates like rule number one of the
speed run, which is that I play the
moves that I would play in a in a real
game. And in a real game, I would go
queen h4.
But, hopefully I can be forgiven for
that.
What was I going to say? Yeah. So,
that's why
I always say that if there's only one
thing that you study in chess, it's
tactics.
Because everything ultimately boils down
to tactics, as it does here.
Bishop f4, queen h4, bishop takes d6,
queen takes h3 is checkmate.
And white simply has no way to defend
both Our opponent doesn't find the move.
The move, by the way, was knight to f5.
I'll unpack this after the game. Forget
about it for now. Here, the follow-up is
obvious. Now, we bring our queen into
the attack with queen to h4, of course.
We should never give up this knight. We
have to force our opponent to take it.
Now, we get the dark squares. Now, we
get the dark squares and we get the
bishop in the attack. And now, our our
attention shifts entirely to the king
side. We're up a pawn,
but we're not resting on our laurels.
Now, white's king is in trouble. We need
to find a way
before white's
coordinated the rest of his pieces to
throw our pieces from the queen side to
the king side. How do we do that?
Well, you might look at this and go,
"Well, okay, the move clearly
is knight to f6."
But, again, what does knight f6 achieve?
What exactly does it achieve? Nothing,
because it doesn't threaten knight g4.
White will be able to take with the
queen.
So, there is a move that I like a lot
more, which still involves the knight,
but it does it indirectly.
Now, what's one of the main rules of
attacking? Well, when you're attacking,
oftentimes you want to open up the
center. You want to open up more
physical space on the board, which
allows you to attack more efficiently.
So, the move e5 actually comes to mind.
I really like the look of e5.
If you wanted to approach this more
positionally, you could drop this bishop
back to, let's say, d6 and open up a
line of fire on the d say on the d4
pawn.
But, that's not Naroditsky style chess.
We got to capitalize on our chances and
play e5.
All right.
And d e we play knight takes e5
automatically.
Now, why does the knight on e5
do something and the
knight on f6 doesn't? It It It has to do
with the open e file.
First of all, the knight on e5 is better
placed because it's in the center. But,
second of all, our next move very likely
is going to be rook c8 to e8. And for
the third time in the game,
first time was when we played queen c7.
The second time was when we played
knight to h5. And now, the third time
where a piece is perfectly placed on a
certain square, the circumstances
change, and so does the role that this
piece plays in the larger scheme of
things. Rook was on c8 to pressure c2.
That was a long gone era. Now, it's time
for this rook to participate in the
attack.
How can it most efficiently participate
in the attack? Well, we could put it on
the open file, but that's not the only
thing that the rook could do. We could
also lift it around to f6. Why would you
do that? Well, I'm noticing that there's
a big weakness on f2, and rook is the
perfect piece to use for that.
Another benefit of this move is that the
other rook could join in the attack, as
well. I really like the look of rook to
c6.
We also could have
There's like a million things you can do
here.
Um
And if you're watching this and say,
"Well, why not this move? Why not this
move?"
chances are
those moves are also possible. I'm just
choosing one of several possible paths.
The rook c6, rook f6,
and of course, then we could move the
bishop and open up a direct attack on
the f2 pawn.
Then, when necessary, the other rook
could join in via, let's say, e8.
White is running out of moves. He's down
a pawn. His position is ruined. No
coordination. He's completely lost. But,
we need that crushing blow. Let's see if
we can do it in style.
Okay.
I might have to talk a little bit less
here
during the last part of the game because
I'm I'm I'm trying to find some tactics
to end the game in style.
Okay. So, bishop f1. The first thing I
see when this move is played is that the
c2 pawn has been released, right? And
I'm almost emotionally attached to the
concept of winning the game on the queen
side because that's where we started
everything in the first place. So, what
move comes to mind on the topic of total
flexibility?
Oh, there's a tactic which almost works
and it's beautiful, but it doesn't.
White work. Yeah, no.
It's not even Oh, it's not even close
cuz the square is defend.
Rook c8, queen takes e5.
Okay. Rook c8.
Let's go rook c8.
Of course, did we blunder d5? No, I just
don't care about this pawn.
If we can take c2, the floodgates
officially open and we crash through.
Okay. Let me think here. I I got to do a
little bit of calculation, make sure we
don't, you know, ruin something in the
end because that happens unfortunately
too often with me.
Even in the speed run, I've done it
several times where I lose my discipline
in time pressure.
I have a really nice move, though,
planned after queen takes e5. It's a
super classy move. It's a move that runs
white out of the center.
White has no moves. This is almost
resignable. We need one or two more
accurate moves and the game is over.
Yeah, gazing giraffe, you deserve a sub.
You're absolutely right. The move that I
have in mind is queen takes d5 and then
rook c8 to d8.
And that move is based primarily on some
tactics, which are quite easy to see
because there, if the queen drops back
to e4, it runs into the x-ray. Bishop
takes g3 check wins the queen.
And simply after queen d5, rook d8, the
queen has no good squares. It has to go
back all the way to g2,
out of the center. And then, we could
calmly pick up the pawn on c2. Or we
could do something a little bit more
tactically minded, but rook d8, I think,
is the most accurate move. You could
even play rook d6 here. If you wanted to
be ultra fancy, you could play rook d6.
But, there is no need to be fancy just
for the sake of being fancy.
Even though I'm a hip huge hypocrite
because that's literally just what I
did.
But, here, we're going to play it simply
just because we're in time pressure.
Queen g2 is forced.
Now, you could play knight g4, but I
think we'll save that move for a rainy
day. Knight g4 king h1.
And I'm not entirely
sold on what this move achieves.
Although,
holy smokes, there's a beautiful line.
Oh,
but it's Wait, 1 second.
Just give me a moment here. It's
beautiful, but there's no need for it.
Let's just take c2.
Okay, I'm trying to win in beautiful
style, but this is a dangerous pursuit.
This is a very dangerous pursuit,
but we're going to follow this pursuit
and play knight g4.
Of course, rook d2 ended the game
immediately.
I just want to play beautifully,
if possible.
That would be the cherry on top. Okay,
he
No, let me think about it.
I think the simplest is rook d2.
Okay, I'll leave the beautiful line for
after the game, guys.
Just because
it would be wrong. It would be wrong
of me Wait, actually, whatever. It would
be wrong of me, but I'm going to do it
anyway.
I'm going to do it anyway. I don't care
because it's it's too beautiful to pass
this up.
It's too beautiful to pass this up. And
it's completely winning. I'm This This
line is totally winning. It's just a
little bit less winning than doing it
straightforwardly.
So, the point is white has to recapture
with the queen.
And then, there is an incredible
tactical move. Does anybody see it?
Yes.
And I'm going to play it. It's rook
takes f2.
And if he takes the queen, it's a mate
in the corner.
So, he has to take my rook and then he's
two pawns down and is completely lost.
And if he goes here, that's the very
important detail. Rook d2 almost wins,
but that would be too fancy. We simply
take the queen, removing the defender of
this rook.
Maybe I exaggerated. I didn't mean to do
that. I was just excited to end the game
tactically, and now it's over.
Couldn't resist. I apologize.
And he resigns. Good game.
Yeah.
Rook takes f2.
Of course, knight takes Oh, knight f2
was winning on the spot.
Sorry. I lost my mind. Knight f2 was
winning on the spot here. Rook f2, queen
g3.
Rook g3, rook f2. This was actually the
best win.
So, knight g4 is the top move.
And bishop g3 is the top move. It's just
at the very end that knight f2 is is
superior.
All right. Let's analyze. We've got a
lot to talk about in this game. Lots to
unpack.
Let me pull up chess base so that we can
do a little bit of analysis.
Okay.
So,
we face a London system. I'm going to
load up Stockfish. I have a little bit
of analysis here in a file. Let me pull
that up, as well.
And of course,
uh c5.
So, if you're watching this and you
already have a line against the London
that makes you comfortable, whether it's
d5 or e6 or g6, you should continue
playing it. All right? Um the point here
isn't just to forcibly alter your
repertoire. I'm giving you proposals,
but if you're already playing something
that makes you happy,
you should continue playing it.
Okay.
So,
what are the options here
for white? Essentially, white has a
couple of options. There is d takes c5,
but it's not good and very rare.
There is, of course, the move d5, which
I actually think might be white's one of
white's better options, but here I
actually have a nice line to show you.
Then there is the move that our opponent
played, and finally there is the move
c3. And one of the appeals of the move
c5 is that c3 is actually not that good.
Because here
after queen takes b6, I think white is
like borderline worse.
Here white is borderline worse.
Why is white borderline worse? Because
it's very hard to find a move.
Very hard to find a move. You're
attacking b2.
If white defends it with the queen like
this,
then
d4 falls.
Except it doesn't fall. You can't take
d4 because you get checkmated on c A lot
of games have ended like this on
lichess.
But instead, of course you bring your
knight out to c6.
White has to play e3.
And now you simply play, well, either d6
or d5. Both moves are good.
I like d6.
And white actually can lose this really
quickly. After knight c3, there is a
really sexy tactical move. Let's see if
anybody watching can find it. If you're
watching on YouTube, pause. This is a
standard and super important theme in
the London when you have a queen on b6,
so make sure that you understand it.
Yeah, it's it's this move, bishop to f5.
And
typically there is a knight on b1, so
the idea is that it traps the rook. Here
it's a slightly different um scenario
because you're forking the queen uh the
rook and and the knight, and white is
busted. White has to lose one of these
pieces with check.
Uh so white is already in pretty bad
shape. If he moves the queen, you could
strike at the center with e5. You've got
a huge initiative. White has to find
this move, which looks like it loses to
knight to b4.
But white can save himself with a check.
You drop your bishop back.
Now this is hanging and this is hanging,
but white is bishop b5. And here you
have another sexy tactical move.
Can anybody find this second very
important idea?
And this gives black a stable advantage.
Not knight c2, although you're on the
right track. Knight c2 is just a trade.
I take and you take. No big deal.
It's knight to d3. Exactly. You're using
the pin, making the knight untouchable,
forcing the king out. White has to play
king e2, otherwise he loses the f2 pawn.
Black plays knight f4 e f4.
And here the move that I analyzed a
while ago, it's still the best move
according to Stockfish, is to to
position this bishop on a superior
square.
And if white takes it,
then you play uh you can play bc, you
can play queen c6, and this end game is
just better for black. Better pawn
structure, you've got a nice bishop.
You've got the b file.
You're going to go king d7 e6 and enjoy
your life. You also have a monster
square on d5 for your knight. Okay?
Um so that's essentially why c3 is bad.
There are There is a better move in this
position, which which very few people
know, which which is knight to d2.
Uh and I analyzed queen takes b2, and it
leads to like insane complications. I
think it's much simpler to just go d5
here and get essentially a superior
version of a standard London position.
If white plays queen to b3 here, then
you take on d4, forcing white's hand.
White has to take the queen, otherwise
he loses the d pawn.
And typically, as I've already explained
before, the side that possesses the a
file has the edge. Even though your
pawns are visually a little bit ugly,
black is much more comfortable. Knight
c6 e3 knight b4, and white's got a lot
of problems to solve.
So that's what happens after c3.
d5 is definitely a more ambitious and
and better move. Here my proposal
is to play the move d6.
And there's a rare move that I found,
which I think solves a lot of black's
problems after knight c3, and that's the
move e7 e5.
You're kind of getting this this weird
pawn triangle, but you're forcing white
to commit. If white takes en passant,
then after bishop takes c6, black is
super comfortable.
So typically white goes e4, you develop
your knight.
White develops their knight.
You develop your bishop. And
you might look at this and say, well,
isn't black worse because of the
backward pawn? The backward pawn is a
temporary weakness, right?
Because you are inevitably going to push
d5 because white cannot control this
square enough times. You're going to
push d5, and after that the structure is
going to be symmetrical, and if
anything, I would prefer black.
So for instance, bishop b2, castles,
castles. You don't even need to hurry to
play d5. You can play h6 just to stop
knight g5. And on the next move you can
calmly play d5, and you're doing
fantastic.
So that's en passant.
If white doesn't en passant and plays
bishop to g5, there's a very nice
tactical detail. Here you go bishop to
e7.
And white's actually not in trouble, but
it's a difficult move. It It's a
difficult situation for white to deal
with, because the natural move to me is
e4.
But this runs into another tactic,
knight takes d5, which is one that I've
highlighted many times on this stream.
The idea is that the knight
simultaneously protects the bishop. So
if white takes it, you're able to escape
d5. If white takes the d5 knight, then
uh
you recapture the bishop with an extra
pawn.
The line goes on. White can give a check
on b5.
And you simply move the king over to f8,
where it is completely safe.
And the reason it's safe is because if
white plays bishop c4, you can just
defend with queen to e7.
You can just defend with queen c7. Then
you develop the knight, you've got the
d4 square. The queen on d5 is completely
unstable. You'll chase it away in a
million different ways.
Typically white plays knight f3.
You drop back to e7 in order to
reinforce the d6 pawn. And according to
my analysis, yes, white has enough
compensation for the pawn here, but not
more than that.
By the way, after bishop c4, do not go
bishop e6 because that blunders b7, and
the rook is trapped. Instead, you want
to go queen to e8.
And if white makes, I think the most
natural move in the position, which is
castles queen side, it looks scary, but
white has no targets. And here you can
play a6 in order to prepare b5.
And if white tries to do something
similar like h4, you just go h6 and
cover the g5 square. White is running
out of useful moves.
And the moment white drops the queen
away, it's time for you to start
expanding on the queen side with b5.
This is unconventional chess, I agree.
This is sort of somewhat
anti-positional,
slightly computerish play, but hopefully
you can see that white just doesn't have
a clear-cut plan here.
So after bishop to e7,
white
you know, in many top-level games
actually gives up the bishop pair. And
here I think there's no question that
black is doing well with like
uncontested dark square control.
e4, you can almost transition this into
a King's Indian with g6 and then bishop
g7, and eventually you can prepare the
move f5. This is at least what I
analyzed.
And yes, like you're watching on
YouTube, this is technical,
but
again, you have to ask yourself like
yes, it's a little bit dry and stuff,
but you have to know this stuff because
the London is super popular. If you know
this stuff, it's giving you it will give
you a huge push.
So the analysis that I just conducted
here with e4 knight takes d5. There are
some alternatives, of course. White, for
example, can play knight takes d5.
And I I didn't talk about this, because
this isn't this is just a bad move,
because black plays bishop takes c5, and
here black actually is able to castle.
And if black is able to castle, then
where is white's compensation?
Obviously, this check is not dangerous.
You can just go knight c6.
So in any case, that is bishop g5. If
white plays bishop to g3,
if white plays bishop to g3, then the
bishop is terrible on g3. It's just
biting on granite.
And here there are some really really
cool ideas. The engine actually proposes
h5, which I love. It's a very
challenging move. You're grabbing space
on the king side.
Typically white will respond with h3.
And now watch this. This is amazing
chess. This is like high energy
Stockfish chess, but this is the kind of
engine chess that I really really like
to see. You go h4.
And now you go b5. You exploit the fact
that the bishop is still undeveloped.
Now who can tell me what the idea is
after knight takes b5? And it's not like
there is a specific tactical idea. You
give this check.
But here you make a quiet move. And this
is what I love. You basically play this
Benko Gambit style.
The point is to prevent white
from playing e4. I think most people
most of you are probably thinking let's
go knight e4.
But you don't even have to go knight e4.
You just develop your other pieces. You
go knight b d7.
And white is just in terrible shape.
This bishop, this bishop, everything's
terrible.
And if white goes, let's say, knight f3,
black is almost winning after rook b8.
White's position is collapsing at the
seams. Rook b1, bang, there is this
tactic.
And here is a beautiful tactic for you.
If white plays rook takes, then you
obviously take the knight and take the
rook. What about queen d2? Who can find
the most accurate path to victory? It's
a gorgeous move.
Pause if you're watching on YouTube,
especially if you're a newer player.
This is something that you can
definitely find.
This is something you can definitely
find. Queen takes knight, exactly.
Deflection.
Take the rook.
Fork the queen, and you'll be up a rook
at the end of the line.
So just one of, you know, many many
I just to give you a flavor of
how dangerous this can be.
So the move b5 here puts white under
very very serious pressure.
Um and h5 merely grabs space on the king
side. If white tries to defend it with
his piece. Again, you can make a move
like this
and white's knight is immobilized. If
white moves the knight, immediately you
trap the bishop with h4.
Um 94 instead of queen takes e3 is also
winning. Yeah, 94 immediately is also
winning but less beautiful.
And that basically is it for d5. You go
d6, you go e5. Are there alternatives?
Absolutely. I won't analyze this for an
hour.
White can go also c4.
But here also, I think e5 is quite
strong. Your your strategies don't
change here. Like you basically do the
exact same thing um as you would after
after knight c3.
Um so that's a bit of a road map
uh to conducting that position. Question
my lying in cat, could white go bishop
h4 or h4 after h5?
So real quick,
um could white go bishop h4? Bishop h4
is maybe even better than h3. I just
think it's less
you know, it's it's less likely to
happen in the game.
Um let me just check what what the
engine gives here.
The engine
after bishop h4 gives queen b6 actually.
Interesting. Oh, sorry. Bishop h4.
Which is the top engine move by the way.
It gives queen b6.
Queen b6 rook b1 has to defend the pawn
knight bd7.
Now, oh my god. This is just Look at
this. If white goes e4,
black has knight takes e4.
These tactics I've never actually seen
before in the London. 94 and e4. And
because there are two pieces on the
fourth rank, you're going to take one of
them, either the knight or the bishop.
White loses.
And it's not easy for white to find a
move here after knight bd7. If white
plays knight f3,
then you go e4.
White drops the knight back. You go e3
and you ruin white's entire king side
and then you just develop your pieces
with bishop e7.
You've got a great position.
Um so that's the short answer. Okay,
let's move on to the next slide. And the
next line of course is e3.
For 1 minute, I'll tell you what to do
if white plays dc. If white plays dc,
the best move in my opinion is knight to
a6. And there is some theory here. There
is some theory here but this line is
very very hard to play for white. It's
not good at all. The main move according
to the database is queen d4. And now you
simply play queen a5 check and pick up
the pawn.
So for instance, let's say white plays
c3. Do not play knight takes c5 and walk
into b4. Play queen takes c5.
Here, typically white plays e3.
And the engine likes dropping the queen
back to c6. You keep the queens on the
board. If white takes, black has a
fantastic end game. You've got a better
center, etc. etc.
And after queen c6 knight f3, uh you
play the move d6.
And now e5 is already a massive threat.
It's not easy to defend against. White
is worse.
If white covers, in this case with the
knight, knight c3, then of course, you
can play knight takes c5. And the
difference is that after b4, you have
this move.
With the pawn on c3, the pawn was
defending the queen. So this would lose
a piece.
But with the knight, you can play knight
c5 before knight e6.
You might say, "Ah, but white has a
desperado sack on f6."
No, he does not. You can just play queen
takes b4 and white is collapsing.
Everything is hanging.
Okay?
So this is not a dangerous move at all,
nothing to be afraid of. And finally, we
get to the move that our opponent
played, which is e3. And this is the
topical. We respond with cd e d and
queen to b6.
By the way,
the the uncommon move is c takes d4.
Most people
play the immediate queen b6. That's the
most popular line but I like to take
first because it well, first of all, it
prevents the move queen c1 because this
pawn is hanging. But also, it leads to a
relatively fresh position. Okay. So what
can I say about this position?
Well, first of all, black scores
extremely well in the database, well
over 50%. The most common move is the
one that our opponent played. But what's
good is that it's not really the engine
recommendation. And the engine does give
equality here. According to the engine,
white's best chance at a small edge is
to play knight a3, which is extremely
uncommon.
I think Eric Rosen might give this in
one of his videos but this is not a move
that you play if you come off the
street. Like it's hard to just come up
with knight a3.
What is the difference between knight a3
and knight c3? Well, this leaves the c
pawn free to move up to c3. And that's
the chief difference. You have to keep
this d4 pawn well protected if you're
playing white and you want to play this
in the spirit of the London.
So here, there is a very interesting
move, which is knight f6 to d5.
Forcing the bishop all the way back to
c1.
All the way back to c1.
Um
an amazing line is knight to c4, which a
lot of people play. Even a 2500 played
this move.
What does knight c4 run into? Who can
tell me?
Pause the video if you're watching.
These are all ideas that you will get a
chance to carry out.
And maybe I'll do a separate London
video. It's actually occurring to me to
do a London for black video. Queen to e6
check exactly.
And you're attacking the bishop. You're
attacking the king.
White has to drop back to e3. And now
bang, you play on the queen side forcing
the knight away.
The knight has to move to e5. Otherwise,
white drops the pawn on e3. And now you
develop to c6.
This is a game played in 2016
between two Argentinian players and
black is black is dominating here.
Knight gf3, you go f6.
You attack the knight. Knight c6 knight
e3 intermezzo. fe3 queen e3, you win a
pawn. You have the bishop pair. You're
in great shape.
So knight c4 is a blunder. White has to
go bishop c1. And now the best idea is
to play the move e6.
You develop and open up a diagonal
for the bishop. Here white goes knight
to c4.
You drop the queen back to c7. And I
think that black is doing perfectly fine
here. I have not been able to find an
edge for white in this entire line
according to the engine. Typically,
white plays knight f3.
You play b6 and develop your bishop.
Uh the game Tang against Oparin.
And Eric Rosen has two games in this
position, 2018 and 2021. He lost the
game in 2018. Sorry, he won in 2018,
lost in 2021. Eric in 2021
played knight c4 to e3 against Akshat
Chandra. And he got absolutely nothing.
And if Eric gets nothing, that means
it's equal. Because here you can simply
play bishop to b7.
And uh Eric played knight takes d5
bishop takes d5.
Bishop d3.
But black has a great position here.
Um black has a great position here. You
can play bishop b4 check.
And believe it or not, the king is
forced to move to f1. Because if white
plays c3, then black has bishop takes c3
check. This is what I love about this
line. It's so full of these types of
tactics because your pieces are super
active. And if you block with the
bishop, then you give up e3.
So Eric was forced to move his king to
f1.
Akshat
played uh castles king side and black
has a fantastic position here. I would
prefer black here.
In 2018, Eric played the move c3
uh in in this position.
And c3
I think is even a better move than than
knight e3 but your strategy doesn't
change. You play bishop to b7, which was
not played in the game. And if white
plays bishop to e2,
you have many many different good
setups. The engine likes to fianchetto
the other bishop. I personally just
prefer to play bishop e7.
Um castles and then castle. And knight
f4 is an idea.
And why is black worse here? Black has a
completely healthy structure. You can
play knight c6. You can push b5.
And I really think that if you're if you
like active positions, this is this is
the way to go.
And that's that's all there is to it. As
long as you remember knight to d5
and and e6, you're going to be in great
shape against the London.
Last theoretical remark and then we will
actually focus on the game itself.
I might have to divide this into two
parts because there there there's so
much to talk about here.
What happens if white plays b3? Well,
nothing happens if white plays b3. You
simply play d5 here.
And and white has permanently weakened
all of these queen side squares. This is
like an inferior version of the game.
The one big thing to remember is that
knight f3 is always met with bishop g4.
If you miss the opportunity to do that
and you play knight to c6, you run the
risk of allowing a move like knight e5.
In this specific instance, no, knight e5
is impossible. But typically, your
instinct should be to go bishop to g4 in
response to knight f3. So this is
nothing to worry about.
Okay, knight to c3.
Hopefully, I'm not boring you to death
completely. And now we play the move
which I really really like, which is a6.
Main line, black scores 59% here in
classical OTB games according to the
database. That's a staggering score for
the London.
That's a staggering score for the
London. And rook b1 is not the best
move. After this move, I think black's
position is preferable. I think black is
slightly better.
The correct move here
um and the best way to maintain equality
for white is to play this typical London
idea a3,
which is one that you're probably
familiar with if you've done puzzle
rush. This is the idea and the queen is
trapped.
Uh so here, you obviously adhere to the
general strategy. You play d5. The main
move is knight f3.
You can play bishop g4.
And black has a great position.
Uh Andrew Tang against Jeffrey Xiong,
2021 Speed Chess Championship.
Continued knight to a4 was Andrew's
move.
Um Andrew's the only one to play this
move. That's a decent move but it
doesn't do anything. You play queen a5
check. And after c3, what did Andrew
overlook? Actually, sorry, it's not a
decent move. That's not what I meant to
say. That's not what I meant to say.
It's a bad move. Why?
Why?
Because you take an F3. The queen is
overloaded. Can't take with the queen,
you have to take with a pawn and just
look at this. And now black plays E6,
black is slightly better.
So again, Andrew's struggling, which
means this is a good line. Eight games
in the database against Bishop B2
and black has won all eight games. All
of them have been won by black including
a 2197 who beat a 2500.
Rina Jumabayev has played this with
black 2650. And the reason is because
this is just a bad I mean London players
hate playing with a knight on C3 because
they hate having a weakness on C4.
That's not what they signed up for. They
signed up for the exact opposite. Black
just plays E6.
White typically castles here.
And here
the most
thematic approach is to play Bishop F3
Bishop F3 Knight C6 and to put pressure
on the pawn.
The engine also likes the move Knight B2
D7
which I think is an entirely reasonable
alternative. You're covering the E5
square.
And uh two games continued to Rook B1.
And now you play Bishop D6 and you have
essentially like an excellent version of
an exchange Caro.
Now I keep mentioning the exchange Caro.
You're like, why are you mentioning the
exchange Caro? What am I talking about?
Well, in the exchange Caro you get a
very similar structure after D5 EDCD.
This is a type of position which can
literally come out of a London. This
structure. And the most common way that
it comes out of a London is if let's say
here black plays C5 white plays E3. This
is the same structure and it can even be
the same position.
Right? It could be literally the same
position. If white plays Bishop F4, you
have yourself a London eventually.
Okay.
So in the exchange Caro
a lot of beginners play the move knight
to C3 here. Knight to C3 is well known
to be a serious positional mistake
precisely for the reason that the D4
pawn now becomes a serious weakness and
black starts to attack it.
Does that make sense? That is why white
is advised to play C3. That's the whole
backbone of the London.
Okay.
So back we go to the game. That's what
you do if white plays A3. After Rook B1,
the strategy doesn't change. We play the
move D5.
Let me see if there's still games in the
database. There are actually a lot of
games. Sadwani against Oparin. Now
Raunak played H3 here
which in the context of of the game you
don't know why he played H3, but this is
not dangerous either. Here black can
develop the bishop to F5. That's what
Grischuk Oparin did. Sadwani played
Knight F3. Oparin played E6.
Sadwani played Bishop D3. Yeah, you've
avoided Bishop G4. Big deal.
Big deal. You're still You still have a
great position. This was a blitz
tournament by the way, but still Oparin
played great. And just Bishop takes D3
Queen takes D3
you can play Bishop to E7
castles Knight C6. I mean zero problems
in
black's position. The position is equal.
Now if you were playing white here, what
do you think white should do to make
sure that the position is equal? What is
the best way to make lemonade out of
lemons if you're playing white? Who can
tell me? And this is a good idea uh if
you're a London player, first of all get
out of my stream, but second of all you
should know this idea. If for some
reason in the unlikely event you have a
knight on C3, it is often advisable to
move the knight back. Yeah, Knight D2.
And then to follow up with the move C3.
As unpleasant as it is to give up the E4
square and yes, we would play Knight E4
here. Still it's important to keep this
pawn protected. Black is doing great
nonetheless.
So
white plays Knight F3. We play Bishop to
G4. There are still games in the
database, actually quite a few of them
and even some grandmaster games.
First time this occurred was in 1995.
Uh Bishop E2 all 11 games featured this
move.
Knight to C6 uh four games in the
database with this move. Our opponent's
next move is not a novelty. Three games
in the database
uh with with this move. So we're still
following a couple of classical games.
E6 and already black is slightly better,
of course. Castles.
Bishop to D6. Man, when did we deviate
from these games?
Um our opponent played H3. One game
continued H3 in 2019.
Bishop H5.
And the point of deviation was here. A3
is technically a novelty. It's not the
greatest novelty in the world, but it is
technically a novelty. But if Wang is
watching this stream and he's wondering
like where exactly did white become
worse, I think the moment where the
position goes from equal to worse is
here. I think after Bishop E3, black's
position is just fantastic. This is the
last chance to claim equality and I
think the way to do that would have been
to play Knight to E5.
And the idea is that after Bishop takes
E2, which is forced, you you can't take
the pawn. The bishop is hanging.
White takes back with the knight. White
takes back with the knight. And this is
an extremely common idea to take back
with the knight in order to be able to
play C3 and the position is completely
equal. It's likely to end in a draw. E6
C3 blah blah blah, you know.
Uh for example I don't know. Knight E5
Bishop B5 Bishop B7 and
both sides are are extremely solid here,
but you're super happy with black.
Um
in any case
uh this was I think the last chance to
to cleanly equalize because already here
you can play Knight E5.
But it doesn't come with quite the same
effect. And I think white should have
still played Knight E5 and the situation
kept getting worse the more development
moves we played because eventually
Knight E5 stops being possible.
So E6 castles Bishop D6 H3 Bishop H5 A3
kind of another waste of a move. I think
Wang didn't know what to do.
And here I really really like Queen to
C7. The concept of
um the concept of a piece having already
done its job on a square. It
queen
did tremendous things on B6, but now
it's time to move it to a a square where
it's more
well coordinated with the rest of the
pieces essentially. And of course the
tactical idea is that B4 is now
temporarily prevented
uh due to Knight takes B4.
Simple tactics. Discovered attack.
You would You take the knight back,
you're up a full pawn. Oh hey Archers.
Okay. So white played Queen E2 which is
a completely understandable move
uh defending the knight.
And there's still a game in the database
by by transposition. But here already
white is in very serious trouble. The
computer evaluation here just so you
know is minus over plus. It's around
minus one.
So it's not just like white is
uncomfortable. White's position sucks
here because white has no plan.
His position is full of weaknesses,
super passive and black has very
clear-cut ways to improve his position
which is exactly what we did.
And our opponent just doesn't know what
to do. King H1. We continue to improve
with B5.
And B4 I think is honestly what takes
this position from much worse to very
close to lost. I wouldn't call white's
position lost just yet, but I would call
it borderline lost. And this is panic.
Right? B4 is the product of our opponent
just not knowing what to do.
What could I propose here with white?
Not much. I think white's position is
awful.
Perhaps the most practical move is to
try to get some pieces off the board. To
try to get these bishops off the board.
When you're extremely cramped
the kind of textbook method of trying to
generate a little bit more breathing
room is to trade pieces. So the move
that I would actually make is Knight to
G1
which I know is sad. Yeah, it's very
sad.
But at least you're trying to get some
stuff off the board. Here at least
you're coordinating your knights.
And then you could proceed perhaps to
try to get the bishops off the other
bishops off the board with Bishop to F4.
Uh so that's what I would do.
There was a question during the game, is
Bishop to G5
uh a dangerous move?
And the answer of course is is no.
And to illustrate that
first of all, there is the move Knight
E4 here. But let's say that black plays
King H8.
If white plays Bishop F6 and Queen H6,
you just drop the bishop back to G6.
There is literally not a single idea for
white on the king side because
this is visually ugly, but it's
incredibly solid. And moreover, black
can use this to his advantage by
shifting the rook over to G8 and using
the G file a little bit later in the
game uh in order to generate an attack.
So if you're a newer player the takeaway
from this is that you shouldn't
automatically
take F6 or take F3. You should assess
the specifics of the situation. Here I
wouldn't give up the dark square bishop
if I was playing white.
Okay?
So our opponent plays B4 exacerbating
the situation even further. Immediately
we exploit the um undefended knight with
Rook F to C8.
Good move by our opponent. Rook B3.
And I'm really really proud of the move
Knight B8. I think Knight B8 from a
positional standpoint is an excellent
move.
Um and it's an instructive move and it's
it's an idea that most of you guys
should be familiar with. But I all I am
very partial in general to uh retreating
knight moves. I love retreating knight
moves and I love them particularly when
they're part of a larger uh maneuver.
Just a moment.
Of course there is a very very famous
uh retreating knight maneuver. I I would
even go so far as to call it the most
famous retreating knight maneuver in the
history of chess. This is a game that is
shown
to all Russian schoolboys. It's like the
ultimate classic Russian schoolboy game
and the Russian schoolboy move.
And you will be among the
lucky
lucky ones to acquaint yourself with
this game. Perhaps some of you have even
seen this move.
I really This move made a huge
impression on me when this game was
first shown to me as as a kid. It is
white to play in this position between
as you can see Aaron Nimzowitsch and
Akiba Rubinstein two old masters
top players in the world and in this
position white makes a move that made a
huge impression on me.
Does anybody know the move that Mr.
Nimzowitsch played in this position?
Anybody know?
He plays a retreating knight move. Well,
there's exactly one of them and that's
the move knight to h1. And as you can
see by the arrows he's going to g5 and
he's going to g5 in order to deliver
checkmate to the white king.
Most students who I've given this to
they start by proposing this move
because it feels you get a rush from
putting that initial but it doesn't do
anything. Black just plays g6 and forces
the knight back.
Whereas the knight on g5 is going to be
a lot harder to kick away because it can
always jump into e6 or if the
circumstances are right it's f7.
So
the way that the game continued
and this is important, right? When
you're conducting a maneuver a lot of
people think okay, I want to go this
this this and this and then you close
your eyes and you make these four moves
come hell or high water. You freaking go
knight h3 no matter how many pieces you
give up. That's not how real chess
works. In in reality
sometimes you make two maneuvering moves
then you react to your opponent's move
which is exactly what Nimzowitsch does
here and then later on you continue the
maneuver.
Right? Here is exactly what Nimzowitsch
does. He plays rook f1 and says no no no
no I'm not giving away the e file. I can
play knight h3 whenever I want to but I
need that e file for myself.
And now he continues the maneuver.
And here black attacks the queen so he
moves the queen. So the interesting
thing is that the knight actually didn't
get to g5
until move 30. They made a bunch of
moves
and only when Nimzowitsch was ready did
he pave the way for the completion of
the maneuver which is really what makes
it so beautiful.
And then in this position he makes
another incredible retreating move queen
to e1 infiltrating through the center.
And now bang
and now bang on the other side of the
board. The idea
is to open up a pathway for the bishop
to d6. This is just unbelievable chess
and Rubinstein ended up
giving away a piece because
if he plays ab then white just gets his
bishop
white just gets his bishop into the game
via b4.
Bishop b4 bishop f8 like this. Just look
at these maneuvers and you might look at
this and say well I there's no way I
would ever find this. Just appreciate
it, you know, just enjoy it. Let this
sink in. And you never know what kind of
stuff you will be able to find in the
game.
But this is where I drew the
inspiration. The move knight to h1
retreating knight moves are always fun
to play.
There's also simpler examples.
It is white to play.
If you're watching on YouTube pause for
a bit see if you can figure out what
Jaan Ehlvest played the Estonian
grandmaster in this position.
Well, first you identify the weak
square.
And the weak square
is quite clear. It's it's d5, right?
This is the square is just a huge
weakness. Often times when there's a
backward pawn that the square in front
of it is prime real estate and the move
is knight you guys are on a roll. Knight
to a1. Everybody's finding it. And the
knight is going In this case it went
straight to d5. Like he didn't even care
what black was doing. He went straight
to d5. And remember I talked about how
you want to occupy a weak square with
pieces rather than pawns? Well
technically this is an exception to the
rule but here if black takes it white
simply wins a piece.
White simply wins a piece. White wins
the knight. But here's the thing.
Black moved the knight
and then black moved the other knight
and white still played a5. So you might
say well I learned that
you know, in this case if I were to
follow the rules black would play bishop
takes d5. But this is the concept of
transforming your advantage. Yes, we've
given up the monster knight on d5. Yes,
the d5 square is no longer weakness. But
white a lot in return for that. In
particular white has a fully improved
pawn structure. The pawns have gotten
braces.
In addition white gets a big diagonal
for this bishop. In addition the rook
has no squares. In addition the pawn on
d5 restricts the black knight. So
advantages in chess positional
advantages they change hands a million
times, right? And the type of advantage
changes throughout the game and you have
to be ready and willing in many cases to
give up something that you hold dear.
Think in literature there's the phrase
kill your darlings where I think writers
often recommend to delete your favorite
sentences because you're emotionally
attached to them. Same thing with
pieces. Never giving away this knight.
You have to be ready to It's like a
chemist pouring stuff from one beaker to
another.
You got to be ready to transform your
advantage. So for instance here what I
would do is attack the b6 pawn.
And after knight to d7 I'd say as a
result of the move cd you now have this
move. This move threatens bishop takes
d7 and rook takes b6 and hopefully you
can see how this is kind of working.
Okay.
One more example
one from one of my games in which I
violated the rule about not occupying a
weak square with a pawn
but it I think illustrates another type
of exception to that rule.
Okay. Now this is a very primitive
example because the position in which
this example starts is already
completely winning and I don't like
examples like that because when you have
a completely winning position it it
dilutes the effectiveness of any any
given move.
But still I think you'll appreciate
this.
Still I think you'll appreciate this.
Here's a game that I played in 2006
in the Pan American Championships in
Ecuador.
And in this position I'm up a pawn and
I'm dominating. My opponent just played
knight takes e5. The e5 square is weak.
What did I take back with and most
importantly why?
This is a classic example of
transforming your advantage. Of course I
took with the pawn.
Positional rules would dictate that you
want to take with the queen. But no, I
took with the pawn. What is the
advantage that I'm getting?
I'm getting the d6 square. I'm simply
exchanging one weakness for another. Now
the d6 square is weak and I have just
the machinery to put a rook on it. Rook
a e8 and I pre-moved rook d6.
And then I doubled on the d file. The
other big advantage is that you get the
d file.
And I won very easily by snapping off
another pawn and my opponent resigned.
Okay, so hopefully you're starting to
appreciate
the general concept here.
All right.
On we go to
the the speed run game.
Okay, so knight b8.
Our opponent I think makes another
mistake.
Not a big mistake but I think after
bishop d3 the position is officially
lost. I would say that if if we had to
draw a kind of a an arc of the game I
think after bishop d3 bishop f3 white's
just got too many weaknesses. I ran this
in the engine and very interestingly
white actually had a chance
to develop some serious counterplay.
And I saw this move but I didn't fully
appreciate it. Does anybody want to take
a guess
at what white should have done in this
position?
It's essentially the only thing that
white can do in order to gain
counterplay. Some of you are probably
thinking g4. This is not counterplay.
This just weakens your position even
further. What does g4 do? It's a one
move threat. Doesn't do anything. Our
bishop is excellent on g6. You need to
look at the other side of the board.
Muhamedov got it. The move is a4.
And this looks like a crazy move because
black could just take on a4.
Black can just take on a4.
And it seems like you can't take back
because c2 falls. That's the whole point
of our play. But as
as often happens the engine finds crazy
ideas out of nowhere and this is a
perfect example. After queen takes c2
white simply takes back. This is like so
hard to understand. White takes back.
White plays bishop to d3.
And after rook c7 white plays this move
knight h4.
And apparently white is not that much
worse.
And the reason that white is not that
much worse is because this knight is
coming to a monster square on c5. Once
the knight lands on c5 we have a
weakness on a6. White's pieces are
actually quite nicely placed now and
black's advantage is greatly limited. So
after a4 black actually should respond
and meet fire with fire. The best move
here the way to keep an advantage is
knight to e4. But after knight takes e4
pawn takes e4
white is supposed to go knight g5
fearlessly and the position gets very
tactical very tactical. And this is
exactly what you want. If you're on the
defending side and you feel like you're
running out of chances. This is why my
coach would always tell me and would
hammer this into my head make it
tactical. Right? You feel like the game
is slipping away from you.
Even if it's unsound even if you feel
like not this this move has no chance of
working. Your opponent is going to be
uncomfortable if they suddenly have to
deal with a whole new set of challenges.
They suddenly have to calculate. They
suddenly have to worry about king
safety. Whereas earlier they were just
chilling enjoying complete positional
domination. That is the underpinning of
the move a4. It makes things tactical
and you don't need to calculate these
moves out completely.
Does that make sense? I don't want to
get into the the weeds here. You can
analyze this yourself with the engine.
Technically because of this knight b8 is
an inaccuracy
if white had found
you know, the insane move a4. But still
I like knight b8 from
the standpoint of
you know, positional mastery.
Okay.
So once our opponent missed this chance
and allowed bishop f3
is that ship has sailed. I mean maybe
white can play a4 now.
Uh but but I don't think it's nearly as
effective. I think after a4 here black
can just play knight b6 anyway.
And,
just get this knight to c4.
And, the point is after bishop c4 or
queen c4, the rook is hanging and you
will recapture the pawn on b5. Still, I
think white should have played a4.
Still, I think this is essentially the
only chance.
Um
after white played rook g1,
we played
g6. Still, a4, right? It It just was a
move that our opponent wasn't looking
for. Right? I don't think our opponent
was thinking that actually white is the
one who can develop counterplay on the
queen's side because this b5 pawn is a
serious weakness.
Our opponent played knight e2.
And, now the ship has officially sailed
because now a4 is no longer possible. We
simply take on a4.
And, again, the move knight h5. What is
the idea? The idea is that the knight on
the rim controls less less squares, but
it controls the important squares. It
controls g3 and f4 and thereby it
restricts the knight on e2. Thereby, it
restricts the knight on e2.
So, the takeaway from this particular
situation is that you should never
assume that just because the knight is
on the rim is bad. In fact, knights on
the rim can be
freaking fantastic if the circumstances
um are right. Here is one final example
of a game in which a very strong GM
voluntarily brings the knight
onto the rim.
And, he does it in a style that's very
similar to what I did.
Here it is.
This is the game Ribli against Larsen.
Now, generally Larsen is on the winning
side of these types of games. Here, he's
on the losing side. Who can find the
pathway that Ribli took for his knight?
And, this is easy because I've set you
up for this.
Knight a1. Another retreating knight
move. Knight c2. Knight a3. Now, look at
what Larsen did. Knight c7.
And, here a very instructive mistake
would be to insist on knight b5 because
here there is a perfect example of where
a weak square is rendered inaccessible
by the fact that a pawn sits on it.
You're not exploiting it and here black
can just transition to counterplay on
the king's side. So, God forbid you
don't go knight b5 here. You sit on a3.
What is the benefit of sitting on a3?
Well, you have black completely tied
down. Anytime black moves this knight
away from c7, you immediately jump into
b5. So, yeah, technically white's knight
only controls two squares, but it's
still an incredible knight. Does that
make sense? And, eventually, guess what
happened? Eventually, Larsen
he moved his knight away.
It happened many many moves later.
And, finally, Ribli
eventually, eventually, eventually
he put a knight on b5. It was move 45,
but eventually it happened and that
knight essentially won the game. There
were a lot of inaccuracies along the
way, so I won't analyze the game itself.
That's not the important part.
Hopefully, that makes sense.
Okay, back we go to the game.
And, of course, there was also the
benefit that we've opened up a pathway
for our queen. And, that's exactly what
we did. f4 and queen to d8 preparing to
go to h4. And, now the cherry on top,
knight takes f4. But, actually,
tactically, this is an inaccuracy.
Tactically, it was a better idea to
start with this move and then play
knight takes f4. And, that is because
white had this crazy resource, knight to
f5. Which is a move you might be looking
for, so you might be like, I'm tired of
this game. But, you might be looking at
this move and saying, I I don't get this
move at all. What is it do What What are
we What's happening? Well, it's a simple
move to understand, actually. It's much
simpler than it seems. First of all, for
newer players, did we blunder a knight?
No, because here, queen h4 is a double
attack. Attacking the bishop and if the
bishop moves, then you deliver a very
powerful checkmate on h3. White has same
no way to defend both at the same time,
essentially.
But, uh
what is the purpose of knight f5?
Who can explain this move
in general terms?
How do you find a move like this?
Pin. So, first of all, you're using the
pin. But, the basic idea is that you're
forcing black to play ef.
Because black does not have time for an
intermezzo. If black takes the bishop,
then you take the bishop and suddenly
everything is hanging.
The point is that after e takes f5, you
play bishop takes f4.
First of all, you've stopped this move
because now the bishop can block the
attack.
Whereas, if we compare this to um
this position, the knight is obstructing
the bishop. So, that's the kind of
tactical point of this move. The
positional point of this move is that
after the trade, you've gotten some
pieces off the board, so white's a
little bit less cramped. Black's pawn
structure has been damaged. The d5 pawn
is a weakness. White is threatening
bishop takes f5 and black still has
quite a bit of work to do. King h8,
black is winning,
but white at least can try to defend.
You know, you want to hear something
crazy? You know what the engine proposes
in this position? You'll never believe
this. You know what the chess.com engine
proposes? Rook c1 to a1 and a4.
So, this plan of a4 is still available
for white to generate counterplay on the
queen's side.
Which just shows you how engines always
aim for active counterplay. That's like
all they do.
So, this a4 pawn lever, you're never
going to forget.
But, by the way, if you're a Sicilian
player,
you shouldn't be looking at this and
saying, "Oh, this is crazy." Because in
the Sicilian
in the open Sicilian and in the Najdorf,
this is like one of the most standard
ideas for white. If not the most
standard. So, for instance, every
Russian schoolboy knows that in the
Najdorf, you're not supposed to play b5
too early.
Okay, you're not supposed to play b5 too
early. Why? Who can tell me why?
And
this this will show me who's paying
attention.
Essentially.
And, this actually happened in one of my
games.
Because of a4, exactly.
And, um
I had a game just like this.
I had a game just like this many years
ago.
Uh where my opponent, who was about
1900, you know, pretty good player,
but he he did exactly that. He played b5
prematurely in the Sicilian. My coach
had already taught me the importance of
chipping away at the pawn structure like
this and what ended up happening was
that immediately black started paying
the price because his pawns are now
disjointed.
And, black can't rejoin them because the
b5 square is going to become a massive
weakness. So, my opponent ended up
giving away a bunch of squares and his
entire queen's side collapsed in a
matter of a couple of moves. So, this is
the concept of borrowing ideas from one
opening to the other. You learn about a4
in the Sicilian, you play it in a
London. That's why people who are
obsessed with like, "Okay, this is the
opening I have to play. I have to play
it for the rest of my life."
Chess is a universal language. If you
build a solid foundation for yourself
where you understand
the sort of rudiments of positional play
and you collect a bunch of these ideas,
you'll be able to play a lot of
different openings pretty decently. You
might not know the details, but you'll
be able to play it
you'll be able to play sound chess.
Okay.
And, finally, the home stretch of this
game.
In the game, our opponent missed
this idea, which is totally
understandable. Knight f5 is a very
difficult move. After king h2, queen h4,
the game is totally over. Now, the game
is over because we have up a pawn and
black is collapsing. And, we open a
second front with e5.
We get the knight into the game.
And, now rook c6, I think is a super
accurate move. Super accurate move
because it keeps maximum flexibility and
it involves everybody. It's better than
rook e8 because if you play rook e8,
like, wait, what about the other rook?
Black gets the other rook to go to c8,
but here you have so many ideas. You
have the rook lift, but you're also
staying on the c-file, so you're
maintaining flexibility and it came in
handy.
It came in handy. Because once white
moved the bishop, I realized that, wait
a second, now this pawn is weak. You
immediately switch to the other side of
the board.
Queen takes d5, rook d8. Of course, we
could also play rook c2. It doesn't
matter. Rook takes c2 and I am a little
bit mad because this was correct.
The knight is untouchable. f2 is
hanging. White has to do this.
And, I'm mad at myself that I didn't
play this move because knight f2 is just
ending the game immediately.
And, what I realized consulting the
engine, this is kind of what happened in
the game except it happened in a
different move order. In this position,
white actually has a move that I missed.
White has an annoying move. And, that
move was a rook to g2.
And, the game actually goes on. I would
not like to have this against Magnus.
Because
black is up two pawns here, but
amazingly, it's actually not so easy to
win this because the a6 pawn is a huge
weakness. And, white's rook suddenly
jumps into f6 and suddenly, black is
experiencing some problems. Because, you
you know, you don't want to go rook a8
because then you're super passive and
you're tied down to this pawn.
So, it's a better idea for black to play
this move according to the engine and
essentially trade on black's terms to
prevent the white rook from getting to
the sixth rank. But, still, you know,
there's some technique left to show.
Completely winning position, you're up
two pawns, but
the game would have dragged on
unnecessarily.
Uh but, I couldn't resist. I mean, a
queen sacrifice to top off a game like
this is
you know, is really really cool. And, as
a nice detail here, you take the queen.
You do not I was considering this move
briefly, but it doesn't work because if
rook takes f2 and like bishop g2.
But, don't go too crazy with this.
Of course, the idea is that this is
checkmate.
And, that's how the game ended. Only 35
moves on the shorter side, but such a
rich game with so many different stages.
All right, there was the theoretical
stage where we followed you know, a
super important line of the London.
Then, after white's first inaccuracy,
the game entered a a of
pre-positional stage where black is
completing their development, and white
is starting to experience problems with
finding a plan.
So, the first serious mistake our
opponent made was bishop e3. Then, our
opponent kind of let us improve our
position. Before was another mistake,
and then I would say the decisive
mistake was to allow the ruining of the
king side pawn structure, after which
white's position is just falling apart
at the seams.
Just too many weaknesses,
and we were able to exploit them by
playing on all three sides of the board,
king side, center, and then queen side,
doubling on the c file.
Okay. Any questions, folks, about this
this game?
Um this was a very long speed run. I
might break this up into two parts, just
to milk a little bit more content off
this, but
I hope that this wasn't, you know, too
dry,
um and too technical.
You know, these kinds of games, for me,
are are important because I can pack a
lot of positional knowledge into my
explanations of these kinds of games,
and I don't want to let that opportunity
go by. Um because I know that I can
really advance help advance your your
positional basics if I'm if I explain
the ideas well.
Okay.
Thank you, everybody.
And thank you for those watching on
YouTube.
I will
go to sleep, which I need to do
immediately.
And I will see you guys later. Let me
raid.
One more thing, folks, if you're
watching and you're new to the channel,
if you like what you see, you feel like
I help you get better,
you know, obviously I supp- I um
appreciate all of the Twitch support and
all of the subs.
Um but also
the YouTube subs are super important for
me, particularly because I fight the
algorithm,
and I don't do clickbait. I, you know, I
do stuff that actively makes the videos
not get recommended to people, so
if you want to put a like,
you sub to my YouTube channel, you
really help me out. I want to get to
500k at some point in my lifetime.
Probably won't happen anytime soon, but
every every sub really counts, so.
Thank you.
Thank you, everybody. Bye.